Take me for example. Um I'm 51. I am on
TRT since eight years. Uh I I take
armored thyroid and I feel fine. I'm
optimized. I can work out. I have a good
libido. Everything is fine. And um what
is the next step in optimization? Would
you recommend trying um growth hormone
or maybe a secret or would you tell me
yeah just leave it alone. You're fine.
>> I think it depends. And I have guys that
ask this a lot. They say, "Hey doc, what
do I want to what can I do? What else
can I do right now?" And I'm like, "Do
to what? Do for what goal?" You have to
have a goal. Don't just take something
to add it to take it. That's what I tell
people. First of all, you need to have a
goal in mind. Something that your
current protocol is not doing.
>> Maybe longevity, but that you don't
know.
>> You can't prove longevity at all. Like,
I can't stand the longevity research. I
I can't stand it because again, you're
looking at these markers that may have
nothing to do with anything. So, in
general, I think the body's pretty
smart. And when you feel well and are
humming along and ticking boxes, that's
the best situation. And that's the good
thing. If you do want to add something,
if you're honest with yourself and you
feel worse, stop taking it. Um, or if
you get nothing out of it, don't take
it. And that's what people get hoodwink
with supplements and vitamins. They feel
no different on them or sometimes feel
worse, but they're like, "No, I just
have to take them because I've been told
I have to take these." No, you don't at
all. I take no none of those. I feel
better than ever, right? I eat whole
foods now. I eat real food. Again, like
it makes a difference. Um, but as far as
GH, like I've been curious myself about
it because I do like being my own guinea
pig and trying things. I'm not against
people trying things. Do you need it?
No. Need is a subjective term anyway.
Like what? Need for what? Um, if you
need it for it, the effects that only it
can give, well then yeah, you need it,
you know. Um, I think I've seen a lot of
people their skin, it can help in the
skin and the nails and the hair health.
I mean, it seems like it can uh a little
bit probably better body composition.
It's not magic. It's not going to, let's
say, melt fat away unless you I think
you hit the high doses like some of
these guys do. And you may see magic
happen, but you also may see some
negative magic happening to your organs
and your blood sugars and things like
that. So, there's always a cost with all
these things. And again, I think it's
worthwhile to explore that. I think GH
is off limits for most people from the
cost perspective. Like
>> I mean we make good money or we did when
we were urologists. I looked at the cost
of growth hormone for like one IU a day
of real growth hormone. There's no way
my wife would have been okay with us
paying for that every month. No way. So
I think that's going to be the big one
is cost prohibitive for most people.
It's very tightly controlled in the
United States as far as legitimate
prescriptions for it. The secrets I
don't even think about them in the same
category as GH because they're just not.
But they do have some benefits. Um, I
tried I Pamearellan CGC 1295 a couple
years ago and because I have a crappy
sleep and I'm a light sleeper, it helped
me sleep better. Now, is that a good
thing from a health standpoint? Like,
how is it inducing that? I don't know.
Uh, I didn't feel worse on it. I felt
like over the couple months, I didn't
really change my diet. I feel like I
maybe started seeing a few more veins in
my shoulders. You know, you you convince
yourself you can see anything, and that
could be a million things causing that.
But I do think my recovery was better
because I was still working out pretty
much the same. I didn't notice the
soreness as long. So again, that's all
anecdotal, but I think that's the whole
point of all this is try it and see. Uh
same thing with thyroid. I've done the
same thing. I take thyroid even though
my panel is normal. I feel better on it.
I'm not getting negatives. I'm not
getting sweats. I'm not, you know,
shaking. I'm not getting high heart
rate. I've taken T3 before. I know what
it can do. I think Armor is way more
gentle. Um, and it just seems to cause a
well-being and mental focus and clarity
and just ticks a few extra boxes. So,
that's my thing is if you're already
optimized on testosterone, lifestyle,
diet, you know, and you don't feel like
there's anything missing, maybe don't
mess with a good thing. If you're like
just want to experiment on yourself,
that's a different category altogether.
But when we talk, I think we used to use
that term optimizing probably too
flippantly and now I've realized there's
a lot of subjectivity involved in even
that word. So, it's really is kind of
like Brick Chavez always says when he's
talking about anabolics, right tool for
the right job. But you got to know the
job that you're wanting to get done and
then explore the tools and see if they
tick the box that you want them to. And
I think it's it's very pragmatic, but I
think that's what all this is boils down
to in the end. Mhm. I read somewhere
that when you're older, maybe over 45,
um the secreta goes are not worth it
anymore because they can't stimulate
enough the pituitary glands.
>> Again, you're you're going into like
they're going into like mental wanking
territory there when it's like, okay, if
I take this and I'm 50 and I get better
sleep and recovery, who gives a crap?
Who cares? All I'm after is that effect.
That's what I want. I want to get it
done. And I don't care about the mental
mechanisms people are coming up with to
try to explain what's going on. I don't
think they can know it. People don't
know as much as they think they do when
it comes to processes in the body. I'll
just put it that way. Uh I think even
Huberman admitted that on on Bill Maher,
you know, talking about like, well, we
only know 10% of what we think, you
know, is true or what. And it's like I
don't think it's that. I I don't think
most of it. They're all heristuristics
and mental models to try to make sense
of how a drug might work, but nobody
actually knows what we know are effects.
What we can see are when we give this
what happens and then you have to
determine if that's a desirable thing.
Well, that's subjective. Then you have
to determine if it's a healthy thing.
That's hard to prove sometimes, you
know, because what if it's fine for a
while and then it gets over time. I
mean, everybody has to choose their own
riskreward ratios with this stuff. So,
I've just way more pragmatic over time.
Hey,
hey, hey.